Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Charles Henry Hart papers
1774-1930, bulk 1888-1918
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Hart, Charles Henry
6.1 linear feet
The papers of Philadelphia art historian and writer Charles Henry Hart date from 1774-1930, bulk 1888-1918, and measure 6.1 linear feet. Found within the papers are correspondence, subject files, scattered personal business records, a file of images of art work, notes and writings, and printed material. The subject files include letters from art historians, art collectors, dealers, and gallery owners.
Provenance
The Charles Henry Hart papers were donated anonymously in 1971.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are 2 volumes of an autograph collection compiled by Charles Henry Hart.
The Archives also has a collection of correspondence between Charles and Clarence W. Bowen loaned by the New York Public Library for microfilming on reels N10-N11. The correspondence concerns Hart's activities on the planning committee of the Centennial of George Washington's Inauguration, New York City, 1889; and Hart's chairmanship of the Committee on Retrospective Art for the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago, 1893.
Additional Charles Henry Hart papers are also available at the Winterthur Library in Delaware.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Charles Henry Hart (1847-1918) was an art historian, lawyer, writer, and director of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts from 1885-1904. He worked primarily in the Philadelphia area and published widely on the subject of eighteenth and nineteenth-century portraiture in America.
Charles Henry Hart was born on February 4, 1847 in Philadelphia, the son of Julia Leavey and Samuel Hart. He graduated from the University of Pennsylvania in 1869 and practiced law until 1894, when he turned his interest to art and writing after suffering injuries in a railroad accident. He became a noted author of books and articles about art, especially portraiture. He had a special interest in the work of Gilbert Stuart. Hart's writings often focused on exposing fraudulent attributions of art work.
From 1882 to 1902, Hart was director of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts in Philadelphia. In 1893, he also served as chairman of the Committee on Retrospective American Art at the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago. Hart was a member of several organizations including the American Historical Association, the Essex Institute, and the Players Club.
Hart's first wife, Armine Nixon, was a great-granddaughter of Robert Morris, a signer of the Declaration of Independence. She died in 1897. According to the New York Times, in 1905 he married Marianne Livingstone Phillips, with whom he fathered a son, Charles Henry Hart, Jr. In 1912, Hart married Anita Beatriz Arabe.
Charles Henry Hart died on July 29, 1918 in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Philadelphia art historian and writer Charles Henry Hart date from 1774-1930, bulk 1888-1918, and measure 6.1 linear feet. Found within the papers are correspondence, subject files, scattered personal business records, a file of images of art work, notes and writings, and printed material. The subject files include letters from art historians, art collectors, dealers, and gallery owners.
Twelve folders of general correspondence consists primarily of letters received from colleagues, dealers, gallery owners, and publishers discussing art-related topics not specifically addressed in the Subject Files arranged in Series 3 below. There is one folder of miscellaneous personal business records.
Subject files comprise the largest and most important series in the collection. The files contain a wide variety of materials, including letters, notes and writings, clippings, reproductions of art work, and photographs. Letters are from art historians, art collectors, dealers, and gallery owners mostly concerning notable subjects of portraits, artists, organizations, including the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, and miscellaneous subjects such as miniature paintings and H. W. Elson's book History of the United States. Several files contain letters from the descendants of John Quincy Adams, Asher B. Durand, Benjamin Latrobe, and Nathaniel Hawthorne.
The images files contain a mixture of printed reproductions of art work, photographs of art work, and original art work compiled and used by Hart as reference material.
Notes and writings consist primarily of notes on art-related topics including the work of various artists, activities of arts organizations, collectors, galleries and museums, sales of art work, and background material about the subjects of portraits. There is also a typescript by Hart containing descriptions of art work to be published in a catalog of the Herbert Lee Pratt collection.
Printed material consists of clippings about Hart and miscellaneous art-related topics, auction catalogs, and an incomplete set of pages from Hart's book Memoirs of the Life and Work of Jean Antoine Houdon: Sculpture of Voltaire and of Washington.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1838-1930 (Box 1; 12 folders)
Series 2: Personal Business Records, 1893-1917 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1774-1922 (Boxes 1-4, 8; 4.0 linear feet)
Series 4: File of Images, circa 1890-1900 (Boxes 5, 8; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 5: Notes and Writings, 1890-1922 (Boxes 5-6; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1822-1925 (Boxes 6-7; 0.8 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Latrobe, Benjamin Henry,1764-1820; Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Pratt, Herbert Lee, 1871-1945; Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts
Subjects-Topical:
Portrait painters; Art historians -- Pennsylvania; Authors -- Pennsylvania; Miniature painting
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Works of art; Notes
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence, 1838-1930, Series 1:; (Box 1; 12 folders)
  Correspondence consists primarily of letters received from various colleagues including dealers, gallery owners, and publishers discussing miscellaneous art-related topics not addressed in the subject files.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1838-1868 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1870-1879 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1880-1889 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1890-1891 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1893-1896 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1900-1905 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1906-1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1910-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Personal Business Records, 1893-1917, Series 2:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Invoices for dues from the Sculpture Society, a stock certificate for 50 shares of The United Editors' Association, and a receipt for a pocket knife.
  - Invoices, a Receipt, and United Editors' Association Stock Certificate, 1893-1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Subject Files, 1774-1922, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-4, 8; 4.0 linear feet)
  Subject files contain letters from art historians, art collectors, dealers, and gallery owners, notes and writings, clippings, reproductions of art work, and photographs pertaining to notable subjects of portraits, artists, organizations including the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, and miscellaneous subjects including miniature paintings and H. W. Elson's book History of the United States. Several files contain letters from descendants of notable people including John Quincy Adams, Asher B. Durand, Benjamin Latrobe, and Nathaniel Hawthorne. The file for Gilbert Stuart contains a letter from Kenyon Cox protesting Hart's opinions, and the file for Robert Morris contains a 1775 paper Continental Currency note. The file for John Paul Jones concerns the controversy over the identification of Jones' exhumed body and includes a photograph of his corpse in 1805.
  - John Quincy Adams, 1909-1915, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Francis Alexander, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - John James Audubon, 1885-1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sir William Berkeley, 1905, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - William Russell Birch, 1892-1914, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
  - Amelia Bloomer, 1909-1910, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - W. W. Boyle, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - James Britton, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - John Henri Isaac Browere, 1896-1912, undated, (9 folders) (Box 1, Folder 25-33)
  - William H. Brown, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
  - John C. Calhoun, 1896-1897, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 36-38)
  - Ludovico Caracci, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Mrs. James Chestnut, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Henry Clay, 1896-1897, undated, (6 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 1, Folder 41-46)
  - James Goodwin Clonney, 1895, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Christopher Columbus, 1892-1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - John Singleton Copley, 1876-1909, undated, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 49-54)
  - The Copley Gallery, 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Captain Nathaniel Cunningham and Family, 1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Alexander James Dallas, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Moseley Isaac Danforth, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - John Wood Dodge, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Sally Ward Downs, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Sir Francis Drake, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Asher B. Durand, 1887-1915, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Ralph Earl, 1913-1916, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 63-64)
  - Jean Pierre Henri Elouis, 1907, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - H. W. Elson's History of the United States, 1896-1907, undated, (22 folders) (Box 1, Folder 66-87)
  - Federico Faruffini, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - George Fox, 1895-1905, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Franklin, 1879-1913, undated, (20 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 2, Folder 3-22)
  - Ed Frossard, 1890-1898, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Sarah Margaret Fuller, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Gordon Family, 1918, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Zilpah Polly Grant (Mrs. William B. Banister), 1909 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Rebecca Gratz, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - John Valentine Haidt, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Sarah Josepha Hale, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Alexander Hamilton, 1881-1897, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - James Hamilton, 1858-1914, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 33-36)
  - Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1893-1903, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Benjamin R. Haydon, 1846-1897 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Gustavus Hesselius, 1896-1929, undated, (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 39-45)
  - Joseph Hunt, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Governor Thomas Hutchinson, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Independence Hall (Albert Rosenthal Scandal), 1917, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
  - Indian Portraits, 1904-1905 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Washington Irving, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Andrew Jackson, 1885-1898, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 52-57)
  - Thomas Jefferson, 1896-1899, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 58-59)
  - John Paul Jones, 1812-1913, undated, (19 folders) (Box 2, Folder 60-78)
  - Matthew Jouett, 1896-1902, undated, (10 folders) (Box 2, Folder 79-88)
  - Horace Kneeland, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Marquis de Lafayette, 1896-1897 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - John Lambert, 1897-1914 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - John Laurens, 1897, undated (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Octavia Walton LeVert, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Abraham Lincoln, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - George Linen, 1897, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - William Lovett, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Mary Lyon, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Gabriel Edward Manigault, 1888-1897, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - John Marshall, 1892-1897, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 8-11)
  - Miniatures, 1888-1915, undated, (15 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 3, Folder 12-26)
  - Robert Morris, 1774-1912, undated, (22 folders) (Box 3, Folder 27-48)
  - Napoleon, 1899-1913, undated, (9 folders) (Box 3, Folder 49-57)
  - Gilbert Stuart Newton, 1890-1892 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - The James Otis Family, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - The Peale Family, 1891-1897 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - William Penn, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1810-1912, undated, (7 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 3, Folder 62-68)
  - Wendell Phillips, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Photographers Who Did Work for Hart, 1896-1898, undated, (8 folders) (Box 3, Folder 70-77)
  - Pocahontas, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Edgar Allan Poe, 1897, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Charles Peale Polk, 1892, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Mrs. James K. Polk, 1907-1909, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Sara Pryor (Mrs. Roger Pryor), 1910 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - John Ramage, 1873-1907, undated, (15 folders) (Box 3, Folder 83-97)
  - John Rand, 1898, undated (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - John Randolph, 1896-1899, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Edward Savage, 1905-1916, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
  - John Smibert, 1898-1917, undated, (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 7-11)
  - Xanthus Smith, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Gilbert Stuart, 1805-1922, undated, (17 folders) (Box 4, Folder 13-29)
  - Major General John Sullivan, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Robert M. Sully, 1891-1897, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Thomas Sully, 1896-1916, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Ida Tarbell, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - William Thornton, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Benjamin Trott, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - John Trumbull, 1884-1906, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - John Tyler, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - John Vanderlyn, 1884-1896, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 38-40)
  - Voltaire, 1907-1908 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - George Washington, 1799-1918, undated, (17 folders; Oversized Material is Housed in Box 8) (Box 4, Folder 42-58)
  - John Watson, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Anthony Wayne, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Daniel Webster, 1896-1900, undated, (8 folders) (Box 4, Folder 61-68)
  - Adolph Ulric Wertmuller, 1887-1914, undated, (9 folders) (Box 4, Folder 69-77)
  - Benjamin West, 1888-1914, undated, (9 folders) (Box 4, Folder 78-86)
  - Lady Diana Whichcote, 1915, undated (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Esther and Thomas White, undated (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - John Baptist Wittkamp, 1891, undated (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Henry Wolf, 1915-1916, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 90-92)
  - George B. Wood, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Robert Wylie, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Four Oversized Galley Sheets about Henry Clay, undated, (from Box 1, Folder 46) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - An Oversized Pencil Sketch about Benjamin Franklin, undated, (from Box 2, Folder 9) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Two Oversized Clippings about Miniatures, 1897, (from Box 3, Folder 22) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - An Oversized Announcement of an Art Survey by the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1899, (from Box 3, Folder 67) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Letter about a Portrait of George Washington, 1899, (from Box 4, Folder 47) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of George Washington, undated, (from Box 4, Folder 52) (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Images File, circa 1890-1900, Series 4:; (Box 5, 8; 0.6 linear feet)
  This series consists of printed reproductions of art work, photographs of art work, and original art work compiled and used by Hart as reference material. Subjects of the art work range from portraiture to landscapes to scenes from American history.
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Unidentified Subjects, undated, (15 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 5, Folder 1-15)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "A," undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "B," undated, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "C," undated, (3 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 5, Folder 18-20)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "D," undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "E" - "G," undated, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "H," undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "J" - "L," undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "M," undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "N" - "P," undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "R," undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "S," undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "T," undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Identified Subjects, Surnames "V" - "Y," undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of "Historical Scenes - American," undated (Box 5, Folder 32-34)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Art Work, undated, (5 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 5, Folder 35-39)
  - Original Art Work, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 40-43)
  - Ten Oversized Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of Unidentified Subjects, undated, (from Box 5, Folder 15) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Ten Oversized Reproductions and Photographs of Portraits of the Biddle Family, undated, (from Box 5, Folder 17) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - An Oversized Reproduction of a Portrait of James Cox, undated, (from Box 5, Folder 20) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - An Oversized Reproduction of a Portrait of Gideon Fairman, undated, (from Box 5, Folder 22) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Two Oversized Reproductions of Art Work, undated, (from Box 5, Folder 38) (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Notes and Writings, 1890-1922, Series 5:; (Boxes 5-6; 0.8 linear feet)
  This series consists primarily of notes on art-related topics including the work of various artists, activities of arts organizations, collectors, galleries and museums, sales of art work, and background material about the subjects of portraits. There is also a typescript by Hart containing descriptions of art work to be published in a catalog of the Herbert Lee Pratt collection.
  - Early Inventory of the Papers of Charles Henry Hart, undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - File of Clippings and Notes on Miscellaneous Topics, 1890-1922, undated, (20 folders) (Box 5, Folder 45-64)
  - File of Clippings and Notes on Miscellaneous Topics, 1890-1922, undated, (7 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
  - Typescript and Galleys for the Pratt Catalogue, 1917, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated, (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 10-13)
- Printed Material, 1822-1925, Series 6:; (Box 6-7; 0.8 linear feet)
  Printed material consists of clippings about Hart and miscellaneous art-related topics, auction catalogs, and an incomplete set of pages from Hart's book Memoirs of the Life and Work of Jean Antoine Houdon: Sculpture of Voltaire and of Washington.
  - Clippings, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
  - Clippings, 1822-1881 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1890-1897 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, 1898-1899 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, 1901-1903 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, 1904 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, 1907-1909 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, 1910-1913 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, 1914 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, 1917-1918 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Clippings, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Clippings, 1922, (5 folders) (Box 6, Folder 28-32)
  - Clippings, 1922, (7 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
  - Clippings, 1923, (10 folders) (Box 7, Folder 8-17)
  - Clippings, 1924 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Clippings Concerning Individual Artists, 1878-1918, undated, (9 folders) (Box 7, Folder 20-28)
  - Clippings Concerning Rembrandt Frauds, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Auction Catalogs, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Pages from Book Memoirs of the Life and Work of Jean Antoine Houdon: Sculpture of Voltaire and of Washington, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)